8th of May, 1945.
At last, the darkness was lifted. The
people celebrated victory over Nazi
Germany.
From the D-Day landings on the beaches
of Normandy in June 1944,
it took the allies almost a full year to
win the war.
11 long months of fierce, often cruel
combat to plant the red flag on the roof
of the Reichstag.
11 months of hopes and fears.
11 interminable months to defeat a Reich
which had promised to endure for a
thousand years.
Those 11 months, with the highest death
toll of the war, left an eternal [music]
scar in hearts and on history.
Summer 1944.
For nearly 5 years, Europe had been at
war awaiting its liberation.
On the 6th of June, the winds of freedom
finally began to blow over the beaches
of Normandy.
On the evening of the longest day, more
than 150,000 soldiers had made it to
land.
By the 1st of July, almost 1 million men
were fighting in Normandy.
The allies had control over the skies.
They were systematically destroying the
infrastructure used by the Germans.
All their convoys of reinforcements were
targeted.
Even Field Marshal Rommel, the head of
German forces in Normandy, was wounded
in an aerial attack.
A joke began to do the rounds in the
German ranks. If you see a white plane,
it's American. If you see a black plane,
it's English. If you see nothing, it's
the Luftwaffe.
And yet, the outcome was far from
settled. The Germans put up fierce
resistance.
The British General Montgomery hoped to
take the port [music] of Caen within 48
hours. In the event, it took 6 weeks and
carpet bombing that flattened the city.
At last, in the final week of July, the
front gave way. The Americans managed to
break through on the Cotentin Peninsula.
Allied troops liberated [music]
Brittany, while General Patton's
rampaging Third US Army liberated town
after town and pushed east.
The liberation of Western Europe was
finally underway. Western France was in
ruins. The population were embittered,
but after 4 years under the Nazi
jackboot, there was finally hope.
The mood was one of confidence. "We'll
cut through Germany like butter,"
predicted a colleague of General
Eisenhower, the Supreme Allied
Commander.
This mood of optimism was heightened,
since on the Eastern Front, a huge
offensive was underway.
Stalin had unleashed Russian forces in
Operation Bagration.
His objective was to seize Belarus
with the subsequent aim of opening the
route to Warsaw, which in turn
controlled access to Berlin.
The Red Army was advancing like a
steamroller, crushing everything in its
path along a 1,000 km front.
More than a million men, 4,000 tanks,
25,000 cannon, and 5,000 planes came at
the enemy.
Nothing could stop them.
The strongman of the Kremlin showed he
had a sense of history. Stalin waited
until the 22nd of June to launch his
offensive.
Hitler had attacked Russia 3 years
beforehand to the day, on the 22nd of
June, 1941.
On this front, the Soviets went from one
victory to another.
Hitler had ordered his generals to apply
a fortress strategy, to dig in in a few
well-defended places to contain the
enemy and force him into long and bloody
fighting.
By imposing a war of movement in 1940,
Hitler was a step ahead in terms of
tactics. By pegging his generals in
citadels, the Führer had now taken a
step back to old school war.
On this front, the Soviets went from one
victory to another.
Vitebsk, Orsha, Mogilev, Bobruisk,
Minsk.
The cities of Belarus fell one by one.
Vasily Grossman, correspondent for the
Soviet Army newspaper The Red Star,
noted
The road to Bobruisk is the road of
retribution.
Here the cauldron of death boils,
swallowing up in merciless vengeance all
those who have not laid down their
weapons and fled west.
To slow the Russian advance, the Germans
carried out a scorched earth policy,
ravaging towns and destroying all
infrastructure.
But nothing [music] could halt the Red
Army. Neither the blown-up bridges nor
the thousands of mines laid by the
Germans.
Their progress was so rapid that they
were running out of fuel. To keep up the
pace, Russian soldiers sometimes mixed
vodka and diesel oil to keep the tanks
rolling.
One German corporal wrote to his wife,
"If the Russians continue in this
direction, you won't have to wait long
before they're on your doorstep."
Hundreds of thousands of Germans were
killed or captured.
Many of them had not yet reached the age
of 20.
Many surrendered
when they had the chance.
The liberated territories were in
flames. The liberated populations had
lost everything, their belongings, often
their homes, sometimes even their lives.
To celebrate what was one of the biggest
defeats inflicted on the Wehrmacht,
Stalin paraded 60,000 German prisoners
in Moscow on the 17th of July, 1944.
>> [cheering]
>> Three years earlier, Hitler had promised
them they would march through Moscow.
A promise now fulfilled.
Attacked [music] from the west by the
Anglo-Americans, from the east by the
Soviets, the Reich was threatened with
sudden collapse,
especially since a major blow was about
to be dealt to its head.
Convinced of the imminence of defeat, a
circle of German officers wanted to
eliminate Hitler so they could open
negotiations with the allies.
On the 20th of July, while the Führer
[music] was meeting with his top brass,
the bomb went off.
The blast caused huge damage.
But despite the violence of the
explosion, Hitler had miraculously
survived.
He suffered a burst eardrum, and a
dressing covered ear, but he was alive.
Not everyone was so lucky.
Several men who were with him were
gravely wounded and would later die.
That same day, Benito Mussolini, who
still reigned over the northern half of
Italy,
>> [music]
>> paid him a visit.
His right arm still in a sling, Hitler
welcomed him and told him, "Duke, a
short while ago an infernal machine was
set in motion against me.
When Hitler showed him the location of
the attack, he said,
"The bomb exploded just by my feet.
It's clear that nothing can [music]
happen to me. My destiny is to pursue my
course and complete my task.
I am more certain than ever that the
great cause which I serve will triumph
despite the current dangers."
Hitler interpreted his survival as a
sign from heaven. Mussolini refrained
from contradicting him.
Before leaving, Il Duce told him,
[music] "After this miracle, it is
unthinkable that our cause might fail."
>> [applause]
>> When the Germans learned that Hitler had
survived, many wept with joy. "Thank
God, the Führer is alive." This was the
sentiment heard on the streets of
Berlin. For in July '44, many Germans
still thought their Führer represented
the only hope of winning.
The very evening of the assassination
attempt, the dictator addressed his
people.
>> The bombing heightened Hitler's natural
tendency towards paranoia. Opposition
figures, real or imagined, were
mercilessly hunted down.
This hunt was led by a hardliner, Major
General Otto Ernst Remer.
5,000 people were detained. The
conspirators were almost all arrested.
This was followed by swift trials.
Certain generals, smartly dressed a few
weeks earlier, now appeared before the
judges in shabby clothes, looking dirty
and haggard.
Erich Hoepner, who fought in campaigns
in Poland and France,
Marshall von Witzleben, former
commander-in-chief of the Western Front,
having had his belt taken away, he had
to hold up his oversized trousers to
stop them falling down.
Judge Freisler, a fanatical Nazi,
showered them with insults.
He shouted so loud that the technicians
responsible for recording this parody of
justice asked him to bring the volume
down.
The sentence gave no recourse for
appeal.
Some 200 people were executed.
The executioners selected particularly
fine ropes to prolong the agony of their
victims.
Among the conspirators was one special
case, Field Marshal Rommel.
He was a national hero following his
victory in Tobruk, but his links with
the plotters
meant Hitler wanted him gone. To avoid
upsetting public opinion,
he gave him a choice, suicide or public
trial.
Rommel opted [music] for suicide
with the assurance that his family would
be spared.
>> [music]
>> The regime staged a grandiose state
funeral for him.
The ordinary Germans knew nothing of his
role.
Officially, the Desert Fox died as a
result [music] of injuries sustained in
Normandy.
Following this brutal purge, Germans
tended to become more fervent to avoid
being suspected of half-heartedness.
One had to show loyalty to the Führer to
the bitter end.
In the army, the Heil Hitler salute
replaced the traditional military
salute.
The regime placed its most trusted men
in the top posts, starting with the head
of the SS, Heinrich Himmler, [music] who
was appointed as replacement army chief.
He now had full powers over 2 million
men.
Goebbels, the Minister of Propaganda,
became the Reich's overall Minister for
War with full powers.
Pleased with these enlarged powers, he
wrote in his diary,
"It took a bomb under his butt for
Hitler to see reason.
The bombing hadn't broken the regime. On
the contrary, it had consolidated it.
However, the allies were still advancing
both from the east and the west.
Farther south in mid-August, French and
American forces landed in Provence.
The GIs of General Patch and the
soldiers of the First French Army
commanded by General de Lattre began to
make inroads into southern France.
Helped by the FFI, the French forces of
the interior, they liberated Marseille
before moving up the Rhone Valley.
But these images of a humiliated
Wehrmacht are misleading. The large
majority of Hitler's soldiers managed to
pull back.
More than 400,000 made it back to
Germany and prepared to defend the
fatherland.
Far from the front, back in Germany,
news reports screened in cinemas strived
to brighten up daily life.
In the summer of '44, despite the
bombardments and while the Reich was
teetering, for many Germans the war was
still distant.
The images testify to the comfortable
lifestyle and folklore traditions that
reigned in the country.
The Germans still had faith in Hitler.
And how could they do otherwise when the
party was omnipresent?
The population was well-fed.
The factories continued to operate. The
administration was functioning and
Berlin Zoo remained open.
It was a wonderful summer and those at
home made the most of it.
The war? What war?
Yet, this bathing filmed in August 1944
was in the town of Dachau.
A few kilometers away, the oldest
concentration camp in Germany continued
to exterminate deportees arrested from
across Europe.
While Germany basked in the summer sun,
occupied Europe remained in the grim
shadow of the Nazis.
The regime pursued its policy of
annihilation.
Between the 7th of June and the 9th of
July 1944, more than 435,000
Hungarian Jews were sent to the death
camps. [music] In August '44, the
crematoriums at Auschwitz could not keep
pace with the number of bodies [music]
piling up.
The SS began to burn them in open pits.
Even as the Allies approached Paris, one
last convoy of deportees was leaving for
the death camps on the 17th of August,
1944.
Only a week later, on the 25th of
August, Paris was [music] liberated.
The Allies did not expect to make such
swift progress.
After 4 years in exile,
General de Gaulle saw France regain its
statehood.
The Americans also [music] made
themselves at home.
The 4th Infantry Division paraded
triumphantly amid the cheers.
The Parisian women hugged their
liberators.
Euphoria could be read on the faces.
>> [music]
>> Many GIs thought the worst was over and
that defeating the Reich was now no more
than a formality.
>> [music]
>> Summer held the promise of victory.
Fall would deliver a series of setbacks.
Since the D-Day landings, the US General
Eisenhower had lost confidence in the
commander of Allied land troops,
Britain's General Montgomery, who had
overseen a string of failures in
Normandy.
Despite these setbacks, Montgomery
demanded to run operations against the
Reich, [music] placing all
Anglo-American forces under his command.
But this demand was unacceptable for
Eisenhower.
To avoid putting all his troops under
Montgomery, Eisenhower divided his
forces into two groups.
The first was under Montgomery's
command.
It would attack via the north
>> [music]
>> towards Belgium and the Netherlands with
the objective of seizing the port of
Antwerp. Once in Allied control, [music]
tanks and munitions could then be
shipped closer to the front.
The second group was assigned to the US
General Bradley and would attack to the
east backed [music] by the armies of
Generals Patton and Simpson.
Things moved fast from September 1944.
[music]
The British under Montgomery continued
their advance and took Brussels.
In the Belgian capital, the population
celebrated wildly as Paris had done 10
days earlier.
>> [applause]
>> The following day in Antwerp, the
victors captured hundreds of prisoners
but did not know what to do with them.
The zoo was quickly reassigned.
Although the Belgian authorities hailed
Montgomery, he made a mistake.
In the rush to invade Germany, his
troops had taken the port of Antwerp as
planned.
But Monty had neglected to clean out the
islands and banks which control its
access.
They were held by heavily armed German
units.
As a result, no Allied shipping could
use the port and supply the front.
This new failure enraged Eisenhower and
for good reason. For two long months,
Allied troops now had to break down
German resistance through dangerous
amphibious operations.
Some 13,000 men died in the process.
But it would take more than that to
undermine Montgomery's self-importance.
The Englishman wanted to demonstrate his
strategic talents to Eisenhower.
Even with the command of half the troops
he had called for, he would succeed.
His aim, to be first to cross the Rhine.
This achievement would erase memories of
his failures and would eclipse the
victories of his rival General Patton.
The American General, a big mouth who
carried pistols with ivory butts, had
liberated town after town moving from
Normandy to the east of France.
Monty was envious.
In a move that looked like arrogance, he
persuaded the skeptical Eisenhower to
give him all available resources.
His objective to launch a huge parachute
operation on Arnhem in the Netherlands.
Code name Operation Market Garden.
On the 17th of [music] September 1944,
20,000 parachutists and 14,000 [music]
combat troops carried by planes and 563
gliders took off heading for Holland.
It was the biggest airborne operation in
history.
The American, British, and Polish
parachutists were dropped behind the
German lines to take a series of bridges
across the Maas, the Waal, and the Rhine
to stop the Germans destroying them.
Once these bridges had been secured,
land troops could go round the defenses
of the Siegfried Line by the north and
invade the Reich.
Monty was sure of himself. Thanks to his
shrewdness, the war would be won by
Christmas.
Unfortunately, the situation on the
ground soon became tricky. The gliders
landed, but some crashed.
The drop zones were too far from their
objectives.
But Montgomery had above all overlooked
one detail, the Germans.
They got hold of a glider and recovered
some equipment and supplies.
But more importantly, they also found a
plan of the operation that an officer
had taken with him in contravention of
orders.
When the fourth Brigade was dropped as
reinforcements, its parachutists were
shot out of the sky like pigeons by
Germans who were expecting them.
In the town of Arnhem, two Panzer
divisions raced towards the British
powers and besieged them.
After five days of dogged fighting,
Montgomery's soldiers were forced to
surrender and the German newsreels
displayed the prisoners.
In total, the allies lost 17,000 men and
only liberated part of the Netherlands.
The failure of the expedition was only
the beginning of a terrible [music]
disaster.
To help Operation Market Garden, Dutch
railway men went on strike.
As a reprisal, the Reich blocked all
food imports to occupied Holland.
The queues lengthened outside the food
stores, which were all but empty.
From October onwards, famine took a
terrible toll. Thousands of civilians
died of hunger.
Henry, aged 10 at the time, recalls,
"Nothing was more important than food. I
woke up in the morning thinking about
food. We used to talk about food all day
long, and when I went to bed hungry, I
dreamt of food."
The Dutch suffered for long months in
what they called the Hongerwinter, the
winter of hunger.
At least 16,000 civilians perished.
While Monty was halted in Holland,
Bradley's US forces were making
progress. In early October, his troops
reached the German town of Aachen.
Germany had finally been reached, but
not conquered.
The Americans demanded the surrender of
the town, in vain.
Hitler ordered his troops to defend the
town to the last bullet.
The First US Army had to take the town
street by street, house by house, in a
fierce combat.
"I don't understand," said one GI, "They
know they will most likely get killed.
Why on earth don't THEY JUST SURRENDER?"
>> AFTER 19 DAYS OF SIEGE, during which a
thousand GIs were killed, the town
finally fell.
The Germans experienced for the first
time what many people across Europe had
felt a few years earlier when they fled
the Wehrmacht hordes.
The taking of Aachen was a symbol.
It was the first German town to fall
into [music] Allied hands.
This toehold in German territory was a
long way from spelling victory.
The Anglo-Americans were stalling in the
face of fierce German resistance. Monty
had failed in his operation in the
Netherlands. The port of Antwerp was
still impractical.
And the hard-driving General Patton, who
was eager to pursue his advance
eastwards, was deprived of fuel.
"My men can eat their belts, but my
tanks have got to have gas," he raged.
He was at a standstill.
In a further twist of irony, part of
[music] his fuel had been attributed to
the British.
With Patton slowed down, the Allies were
unable to exploit the breakdown of the
Western Front.
As a result, the Germans had time to
regroup their defenses, taking up
positions beyond the Rhine. The Western
Front was blocked.
War over by Christmas? That dream had
evaporated.
The war would go on.
On the Soviet side, Operation Bagration
was a success.
Russian advances were impressive.
Between the 22nd of June and the 31st of
August, 1944, their offensives had put
700,000 Germans out of combat. The
troops under General Zhukov's command
covered 500 km in 5 weeks, almost as
quick as the German tanks in the other
direction in 1941.
The Soviets were approaching Warsaw.
In the city, the Soviet artillery could
already be heard rumbling in the
distance. Radio Moscow called on the
population to rise up.
Convinced they would be backed by the
Red Army, the Polish Secret Army
launched an insurrection on the 1st of
August.
But its fighters had only makeshift
equipment.
They seized some German helmets along
with some weapons and a few tanks.
The first days were euphoric. In the
exuberance, barricades went up in every
neighborhood. Everyone took part in the
combat in their own way.
Soon, the Polish controlled parts of the
capital, and their flag flew once again
over a few roofs.
>> [music]
>> These heroic resistance fighters threw
everything into it and drove back the
Germans.
>> The Polish knew the Russians were just
nearby, the other side of the Vistula.
With this powerful ally waiting in the
wings, the insurgents had nothing to
fear.
But on the 4th of August, the Germans
sent reinforcements.
Their mission,
to eliminate the Polish problem by
whatever method.
The city was mercilessly shelled.
Gradually, the Germans retook control of
the city and crushed the insurgents.
The hospital was torched, the wounded
executed.
The resistance movement could have
tipped the balance if it had had
support.
But the Red Army stood on the sidelines,
while the German forces destroyed the
city, the Soviet troops camped on the
banks of the Vistula.
Stalin was unmoved.
He would not intervene.
For a while, he even refused permission
for the Americans and British to use his
aerodromes to supply the insurgents,
leaving them to face slaughter.
He had a dual motive.
He had to allow his troops to recuperate
their strength after Operation
Bagration. The supply core had to bring
up fresh fuel, weapons, munitions, and
spare parts to this new front line on
the Vistula.
Meanwhile, Stalin left the non-communist
Polish resistance to be wiped out so he
could put Polish communists in power at
a later date.
The Anglo-Americans protested, but not
so strongly as to threaten their
relationship with Moscow.
That was the price of the Soviet
alliance against Hitler.
>> [music]
>> The uprising in Warsaw ended in a
bloodbath. Some 220,000
civilians and resistance fighters died.
>> [music]
>> After 2 months of fierce combat, the
guns fell silent.
The Polish General Bor-Komorowski signed
[music] the surrender on the 2nd of
October.
The resistance armies surrendered.
85% of Warsaw was in ruins.
The Polish, who had hoped for support
from the Soviets, now feared falling
into their hands.
As one poet put it,
>> [music]
>> "We await you, red plague, to deliver us
from the brown plague."
>> [music]
>> While the Red Army camped on the
Vistula, to the west, the Allied armies
had at last been able to open the port
of Antwerp, through which supplies were
now flowing. The Americans had reached
the Rhine. The Reich was finally caught
[music] in a pincer.
But despite this attack on two fronts,
the Nazi regime showed no sign of
crumbling.
On the contrary,
the army blindly obeyed its supreme
leader.
In October, Himmler created the
Volkssturm, the people's storm.
This militia recruited men who were not
already serving in a home defense force.
At a stroke, the provincial solicitor,
the teenager in the countryside, or the
village baker found themselves armed
with a rocket launcher to defend the
Reich.
The German people were still solidly
behind their Führer.
They couldn't imagine any alternative to
the Nazi regime.
This was because during the 12 years he
had been in power, Hitler and his regime
had indoctrinated the Germans.
In 1944, the Nazi party still had 8
million members.
There wasn't a family in the country
which didn't count at least one party
member.
For those in any doubt, the propaganda
of Dr. Goebbels endlessly hailed the
superiority of the German soldier and
declared that Allied coalition would end
up unraveling.
His fables persuaded the Germans that
they would triumph.
In December 1944, Germany had been
holding out on two fronts for nearly
five months. The Reich was wounded. It
was bleeding.
But on the economic level, the country
redoubled efforts in factories producing
tanks, planes, submarines, and
munitions.
While they couldn't win the battle in
terms of quantity, German engineers
invented new weapons, like
remote-controlled miniature tank buster
vehicles,
and one-man torpedo submarines.
But above all, Hitler put great store in
what he called miracle weapons.
The V1 flying bombs, which had been
raining down on London since June, and
had killed thousands of civilians.
The V2 was the first ballistic missile
in history.
For several years, they had been
secretly developed in the Reich's
factories.
In the fall of '44, they were finally
ready.
These rockets could carry 1 ton of high
explosives.
Although these retaliatory weapons had a
limited impact, they galvanized the
Germans.
One young man wrote, "All we talk about
is the V2. Perhaps we can launch them
against America. I'm sure that victory
is ours."
This industrial prowess was due to one
man, Albert Speer.
The Führer's architect supervised this
reorganization, which he portrayed as a
miracle.
Because despite the Allied bombardments,
weapons production had actually
increased up to July 1944.
But this unholy miracle bore a name,
slavery.
The Reich exploited millions of workers,
deportees, Jews, communists, resistance
fighters.
There were also labor conscripts rounded
up from across Europe. Prisoners of war
were turned into workers.
Almost 9 million men and women worked in
atrocious conditions on behalf of the
Reich.
German industry could thus keep up with
the war effort.
The Reich was even able to go from being
on the defensive to the offensive.
On the Western Front, the division of
Allied forces into two blocks had left
the sector of the Ardennes dangerously
ill-defended.
That was where Hitler decided to strike.
On the 16th of December, to the
astonishment of the Allies, 1,900
cannons opened fire.
>> Artillery!
Incoming
artillery!
>> In the first few hours, the element of
surprise gave the German High Command an
unexpected success.
The allies thought they were dealing
with a routed army. Instead, they found
themselves facing a fierce
counterattack.
For Hitler, it was a big gamble. He
hoped this offensive might stabilize the
Western Front, convincing the
Anglo-Americans that they could never
win. And who knows, maybe even prompt
them to side with him against the
Bolshevik demon.
The Führer was convinced the East-West
coalition was against nature and was
destined to break up.
Marxists allied with capitalists? It was
simply heresy. This alliance would
crumble. It just needed to be dealt the
coup de grâce.
The Germans made progress, helped
[music] by the bad weather which
prevented Allied aviation from
intervening.
The advance was spectacular.
One lieutenant wrote to his wife,
"You cannot imagine the days of glory
that we're experiencing at the moment.
It is as if the Americans cannot
withstand the might of our thrust."
The fifth Panzer Division captured
almost 9,000 GIs, many of whom were
black.
This gave the Nazi propaganda machine
the opportunity to claim the US Army was
made up of subhumans.
The news spread in Belgium and Alsace,
both of which had only just been
delivered from the brown plague. The
Germans are returning.
Civilians who had only just returned to
their homes took to the road again.
As they prepared to celebrate Christmas,
German families also celebrated this new
offensive. What a wonderful Christmas
present, one could hear in the streets.
Goebbels' pollsters noted, "People are
profoundly happy that we have seized
back the initiative, especially since no
one expected it."
This operation reinvigorated the German
population.
One soldier wrote to his wife, "The snow
must be stained red with the blood of
Americans. We're going to cast them into
the ocean, the arrogant, loudmouth apes
from the new world. They [music] will
not set foot on our Germany."
But, the determination of the German
soldiers sometimes escalated into
bloodthirsty fervor as they committed
numerous war crimes.
On the 17th of December, 69 American
prisoners of war were shot dead by the
SS.
A few days later, in the little town of
Malmedy, the bodies of 86 GIs executed
by the same SS unit were discovered.
Belgian civilians, men, women, and
children were also massacred.
They spared no one.
Meanwhile, chaos reigned on the American
lines. To add to the confusion, German
commandos disguised as Americans had
infiltrated Allied territory, switching
road signs and carrying out sabotage.
The GIs were suspicious of everyone and
everything.
They intercepted vehicles and carefully
checked identity papers.
They were told to ask questions that
only an American could answer.
In one of the most critical periods of
winter 1944, the military police would
ask at every checkpoint, "Who is Donald
Duck's girlfriend? What is Roosevelt's
dog's name?"
Sometimes spies were captured.
The German troops pushed on with their
breakthrough.
They besieged the small Belgian town of
Bastogne, a crucial strategic point for
the success of their operation.
18,000 GIs were defending the town.
In their ranks, the rumor spread that
the Germans didn't take prisoners.
The American soldiers doubled their
efforts.
But the town was quickly surrounded by
Panzers.
The US troops were caught in a trap.
While he was preparing an offensive
further south, General Patton was called
to the rescue.
In midwinter, he swung his army around
90° and headed straight north,
pusing hard for Bastogne.
He had promised Eisenhower that this
maneuver would take him no more than 3
days.
His tanks drove day and night through
appalling conditions.
They had not planned for icy roads, but
managed to keep moving forward.
Meanwhile in Bastogne, the GIs were up
against the Germans and the weather.
Many died frozen in their foxholes.
On the 26th of December, the Germans
looked up at the sky in horror.
The snow had stopped.
The snowflakes had been replaced by the
heavy bombers of the US Air Force, which
pounded the German positions.
Soon after, as he had promised, Patton's
Third Army came to relieve the siege of
Bastogne.
Just in time.
Hitler's gamble had backfired.
The human cost was high. On the Allied
side, 80,000 men killed or injured. The
Germans counted 120,000.
Overall, the battle merely pushed back
the hour of reckoning for the Reich, but
it came as a wake-up call for the
Allies.
They had realized one thing, Germany was
still dangerous.
At the Führer's headquarters, the mood
was one of concern.
Göring suggested to Hitler that he
should seek an armistice.
"The war is lost," he explained.
Hitler replied,
"I forbid you to take any such decision
on this point. If you disobey my orders,
I'll have you shot."
Hitler was wrapped up in his delusions.
He insisted, [music]
"We will never surrender. We may go
down, but we will take a world with us."
Despite the withdrawal of Hitler's
armies on all fronts, five months of war
and chaos still lay ahead before the
fall of Berlin and the defeat of the
Third Reich.
The beast was weakened, but not yet
dead.
And the Germans seemed ready to follow
the Führer to the very end.